Curriculum Vitae



Dr. Pallavi Vyas

Research Associate (RUSA project)
Department of Botany, MLS University, Udaipur (Rajasthan)
Phone: +91(0)7506438010; e-mail: pal.dwivedi@gmail.com

Profile

I am an ambitious, hard-working individual, with over 12 years of teaching and research experience at various national and International educational organizations. Currently I am working as a Research Associate on a project entitled as "Capacity building and livelihood security of Tribal's of South Rajasthan through Bioprospecting, Biotechnological Interventions and Disease Management of Ginger" which is funded under the scheme RUSA. Through my previous and current job, I gained extensive experience of teaching, research and academic writing and editing which supports my suitability for the current position as "Associate Professor in Biotechnology" at Chhatrapati Shivaji Maharaj University, Panvel, Navi Mumbai.

Work Experience

- Research Associate
 Department of Botany, MLSU

 March 2021-Till now
- Science and Technology Teacher
 Engelska Skolan Norr,
 Stockholm, Sweden
 August 2018-September 2020
- Assistant Professor
 Amity Institute of Biotechnology
 Amity University Mumbai
 September 2015 June 2016
- Assistant Professor
 Biotechnology Department
 Sir Padampat Singhania University
 September 2010 May 2015
- Senior lecturer
 Biotechnology Department
 Sir Padampat Singhania University
 December 2008 August 2010

Skills

- Good relations and contacts at Swedish Universities, schools and companies.
- Teaching various subjects including molecular biology, microbial biotechnology, plant tissue culture, animal cell culture, metabolic engineering, analytical techniques etc to graduate, post-graduate and Ph.D. students.
- Expertise in all modes of digital teaching tools and methods i.e.G-suit, microsoft teams, zoom, socrative, etc which are commonly used for theory and practical teaching.
- Preparation of lesson plans, lecture handouts, laboratory manuals, designing course structure and syllabus, preparation of project reports, documentation and analysis of experiment outcomes.
- Scientific Writing like research grant proposals, research manuscripts, research papers.
- Computer knowledge: Expertise with MS word, power point, excel, photoshop, Chem-Bio Draw, Sigma plot.
- Published a book: Deka P C & Dwivedi P (2015).
 Molecular Biology: A Genetical Approach, Wiley India Pvt. Ltd.

Research Interest

- Genetic diversity analysis through molecular markers
- Microbiological analysis of different samples
- Enzyme kinetics and stability studies
- Protein purification and characterization
- Production of value-added products from microbial and plant cellculture system
- Antigen-antibody interaction

Specialization

- Microbial Biotechnology
- Molecular Biology
- Enzymology
- Plant cell and tissue culture

Awards

- DST travel grant to attend 14th International Biotechnology Symposium and Exhibition at Rimini, Italy
- Qualified joint CSIR UGC test (NET June, 2003)
- Qualified GATE-2003 Percentile-88.30, All India Rank-407

Publications-21

(Refer annexure-1 for details)

Book: 1

Research and Review papers: 9

Book chapters: 3

International & national conferences: 8

Qualification

Doctorate in Microbial Biotechnology

Indian Institute of Technology Roorkee (IIT-R), India

January 2004- August 2009

Master's in Biotechnology

Mohanlal Sukhadia University, India

Bachelor's in Science Biology

Mohanlal Sukhadia University, India

Languages

English: Excellent

(speaking, reading, writing)

Swedish: Excellent

(speaking, reading, writing)

• Hindi: Native language

(speaking, reading, writing)

References

Dr. Harish

Assistant Professor Department of Botany Mohan Lal Sukhadia University Udaipur 313001 (Rajasthan) INDIA

Mobile: +91-94144-78466

Email: harish.botany1979@gmail.com

Dr. Bhawana Chanana

Director,

Marks -75.25 %

Marks -74.81 %

Amity School of Fashion Design and Technology,

Amity University,

Pune Expressway, Bhatan, Post – Somathne, Panvel, Mumbai (Maharashtra) – 410206.

Phone: +91-9717677554

Email: bchanana@mum.amity.edu

Place: Udaipur Date: 5th May, 2022

Pallavi Vyas

Annexure-1 Research Publications

Research and review papers in refereed international journals

- 1 **Vyas, P.** (2022). Anti-CRISPR proteins as a therapeutic agent against drug-resistant bacteria. *Microbiological Research*, **257**: 126963. (https://doi.org/10.1016/j.micres.2022.126963)
- 2 Kumar A., Lodha S. and **Dwiwedi P** (2015). Production of Serine Protease Inhibitors from Momordica Dioica Cell Cultures. *Indo Global Journal of Pharmaceutical Sciences*, **5**: 124-128.
- *Dwivedi P., Vivekanand V, Pareek N, Sharma A and Singh R P (2011). Co-cultivation of mutant *Penicillium oxalicum* SAU_E-3.510 and *Pleurotus ostreatus* for simultaneous biosynthesis of xylanaseand laccase under solid-state fermentation. *New Biotechnology*, 28: 616-26. (https://doi.org/10.1016/j.nbt.2011.05.006)
- 4 Vivekanand V, **Dwivedi P**, Pareek N, and Singh R P (2011). Banana peel: a potential substrate for laccase production by *Aspergillus fumigatus* Vkj2.4.5 in solid-state fermentation. *Applied Biochemistry and Biotechnology*, **165**: 204-220. (https://doi.org/10.1007/s12010-011-9244-9)
- 5 Pareek N, Vivekanand V, **Dwivedi P** and Singh R P (2010). *Penicillium oxalicum* SAE_M-51: a mutagenized strain for enhanced production of chitin deacetylase for bioconversion to chitosan. *New Biotechnology* **28**, 118-124. (https://doi.org/ 10.1016/j.nbt.2010.09.009)
- *Dwivedi P, Vivekanand V, Ganguly R and Singh R P (2009). *Parthenium* sp. as a plant biomass for the production of alkalitolerant xylanase from mutant *Penicillium oxalicum* SAU_E-3.510 in submerged fermentation. *Biomass and Bioenergy* 33, 581-588. (https://doi.org/10.1016/j.biombioe.2008.09.001)
- *Dwivedi P, Vivekanand V, Pareek N, Sharma A and Singh R P (2010). Bleach enhancement of mixed wood pulp by xylanase-laccase concoction derived through co-culture strategy. *Appl. Biochem. Biotechnol.* 160:255–268. (https://doi.org/10.1007/s12010-009-8654-4)
- 8 Vivekanand V, **Dwivedi P,** Sharma A, Sabharwal N and Singh R P (2008). Enhanced delignification of mixed wood pulp by *Aspergillus fumigatus* laccase mediator system. *World J. Microbiol. Biotechnol.* **24**, 2799-2804. (https://doi.org/10.1007/s11274-008-9809-0)
- Ganguly R, **Dwivedi P** and Singh R P (2007). Production of lactic acid with loofa sponge immobilized *Rhizopus oryzae* RBU2-10. *Bioresource Technol.* **98**, 1246-1251. (https://doi.org/10.1016/j.biortech.2006.05.004)

Book

10. Deka P C & Dwivedi P (2015). Molecular Biology: A Genetical Approach". Wiley India Pvt. Ltd. ISBN: 9788126553990

Chapters in Book

- 11 Deka P C and Dwivedi P (2016). "Hairy roots and their multiple applications"; *In:* "Biotechnological tools for genetic resources", (Astral International Pvt. Ltd., New Delhi, India, PP-275-308. ISBN: 978-93-51247-74-6
- 12 Singh R P, Vivekanand and **Dwivedi P** (2010). "Laccase regulation and laccase dependent bioremediation"; In: "Industrial exploitation of microorganisms A Techno-Commercial Approach", (Maheshwari D K & Dubey R C eds.) I K International, New Delhi, India, PP-286-301. ISBN: 978-93-80026-53-4
- 13 Singh R P, **Dwivedi P**, Vivekanand and Kapur N (2007). Xylanases: structure, molecular cloning and regulation of expression. *In: Lignocellulose biotechnology: future prospects, (Kuhad R C & Singh A eds.) I K international New Delhi, India, pp: 149-161.* ISBN: 978-81-88237-58-6

International Conferences

- 14 **Dwivedi P**, V. Vivekanand, N. Pareek and R. P. Singh (2010). Bleaching Applications and Scaled-Up Production of Xylanase-Laccase Mixture in an Intermittent Rotating Drum Bioreactor. 14th International Biotechnology Symposium and Exhibition, Rimini, Italy, September 14th -18th, 2010, PP-575.
- 15 **Dwivedi P**, Vivekanand V, Pareek N and Singh R P (2009). An intermittent rotating drum bioreactor for the production of xylanase-laccase concoction through co-cultivation under solid- state fermentation. *3rd*

- Congress of European Microbiologists-FEMS 2009, Gothenburg, Sweden, June 28- July 02, 2009, PP 158.
- 16 Pareek N, **Dwivedi P**, Vivekanand V and Singh R P (2009). Chitin deacetylase from *Penicillium oxalicum* ITCC 6965: A novel enzyme for production of chitosan. *3rd Congress of European Microbiologists-FEMS* 2009, *Gothenburg, Sweden, June* 28- July 02, 2009 PP 158.
- 17 **Dwivedi P**, Vivekanand, Sabharwal N and Singh R P (2007). "Fungal co-cultivation: an approach for simultaneous production of xylanase and laccase under submerged fermentation using *Parthenium* sp. as a novel plant biomass". 29th Symposium on Biotechnology for Fuels and Chemicals, Denver Adams Mark Hotel, Denver, Colorado, USA, 29th April 2nd May, 2007, PP-181.
- 18 Vivekanand, **Dwivedi P**, Sabharwal N and Singh R P (2007). "SSF: a novel strategy for enhanced production of laccase by mutant *Aspergillus fumigatus* VkJ2-4.5 using banana peel as an ideal solid support". 29th Symposium on Biotechnology for Fuels and Chemicals, Denver Adams Mark Hotel, Denver, Colorado, USA, 29th April 2nd May, 2007, PP-182.
- 19 Sharma A, Vivekanand, **Dwivedi P** and Singh R P (2007). Solid-state fermentation for gluconic acid production from sugarcane molasses by *Aspergillus niger* ARNU-4 strain employing tea waste as the novel solid support. 15th European Biomass Conference & Exhibition. Biomass for Energy, Industry and Climate Protection., ICC Intl Cong Centre Berlin, Germany, May 07th -11th.
- 20 Singh R P, Kapur N and **Dwivedi P** (2005). Regulation and engineering of xylanases possibilities and implications. *International Conference on Microbial Diversity, University of Delhi, New Delhi, April* 16th 18th, p 30-31.

Papers in National Conference

21 **Dwivedi P**, Vivekanand and Singh R P (2006). Alkalitolerant, cellulase free xylanase from *P. oxalicum* SAU_E-3.510 using cheaper lignocellulosic materials. *Natl. Symp. Biohorizon-2006, IIT Delhi, New Delhi, India, March 10th -11th, p, 3.*